Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is
קי"ד. Kuf yud dalet. We pick up in the middle of קי"ג
עמוד ב'. Kuf yud gimmel amud bet.
And this is a very short פרק. Perek. We had all the
משניות Mishnayos of the פרק Perek put into one and God willing
by today we will be done with the פרק. Perek. So we
pick up on the actually the top of קי"ג עמוד ב'. Kuf
yud gimmel amud bet. We are a bit behind. Let's see if
we can keep focus and get through this. So נשתטית, Nishtatit, about
ten lines from the top. So we actually had a fascinating גמרא
Gemara about the fact that a חרש Cheresh might not be considered
completely not a בר דעת, Bar da'as, might be a ספק, Safek,
and that actually a position of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, significant as
I said in terms of contemporary discussions. Now we pick up with
the idea that if she's a שוטה, Shotah, if she's not of
her right mind, then she then you cannot are not allowed to
divorce her, even though technically it would work because again a woman
does not have to have דעת Da'as in the process of גירושין,
Gerushin, it's a unilateral act. So אמר רבי יצחק: Amar Rabbi Yitzchak:
דבר תורה, D'var Torah, biblically speaking, שוטה מתגרשת, Shotah mitgareshit, a woman
not of a right non-in her right mind can be divorced. מדי
דהוה אפיקחית בעל כרחה, Mi'dei de'hava apikes b'al korchah, the same way
a woman who can be divorced, who is you know, well, of
a right you know, can be divorced against her will, so it
does not require her participation. So
ומה טעם אמרו, U'mah ta'am amru, that's true, why did they say
אינה מתגרשת, Einah mitgareshet, she cannot be divorced? שלא ינהגו בה מנהג
הפקר. Shelo yinhagu bah minhag hefker. Because since this woman is not,
you know, is not well mentally, then if she is once then
if she's divorced, people will take sexual advantage of her. So of
course if she's not married yet, okay, you do what you can,
you know, parents try to protect her, whatever. But if she was
married, then maybe the parents step out of the scene and regardless
then the Rabbis are going to step in and say once you
the husband have married her, you have, you know, you're responsible and
you cannot just divorce her and let her be taken advantage of.
Well, I don't know, but again, society whatever, they didn't this is
a way they did in order to protect her interests, okay, as
opposed to say, oh, you know, you should do this or should
do that. They said you're not allowed to divorce her and that
hopefully will protect her. שלא ינהגו בה מנהג הפקר. Shelo yinhagu bah
minhag hefker. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: היכי דמי? Heichi
dami? What's the case? אילימא דיודעת לשמור גיטה ויודעת לשמור עצמה, Ileima
d'yada lishmor gitah v'yada lishmor atzmah, if she's of well enough, you
know, mentally that he can, a) watch her גט, Get, you give
her something and she doesn't like, you know, not just, yeah, not
just lose it like a lot of people tend to lose things
like myself, but, you know, but not just like completely not not
understand what it is and just, you know, like, you know, completely
like, you know, just discard it essentially.
So and she knows how to watch herself protect herself from abuse,
so שלא ינהגו בה מנהג הפקר? Shelo yinhagu bah minhag hefker? People
won't take advantage of her. אלא דאין יודעת לשמור לא גיטה ולא
עצמה, Ela d'ein yada lishmor lo gitah v'lo atzmah, so let's say
she's of a mental state where she can't even watch her own
גט, Get, let alone herself. So דבר תורה D'var Torah שוטה מתגרשת?
Shotah mitgareshit? How could you say that it works biblically? ואמר דבי
רבי ינאי: V'amar d'vei Rabbi Yannai: ונתן בידה, V'natan b'yadah, that it
has to be placed in her hand. מי שיש לה יד לגרש
עצמה, Mi she'yesh lah yad l'garesh atzmah, a woman who actually has
something which is considered to be a יד. Yad. A יד Yad
does not just mean physically a hand. It's understood abstractly to mean
it could be in her, you know, yard, under any area that
she controls. But once it's understood abstractly, it also means that even
if it is in her physical hand, if it's put in her
hand in a way that she doesn't protect it to any degree,
that's not considered in her hand. In her hand means in her
protection, in her, you know, on her person and property that is
being protected by her. So therefore, יצתה זו שאין לה יד לגרש
עצמה, Yatzta zo she'ein lah yad l'garesh atzmah, which would exclude a
woman that even that she can't protect even anything you put in
her hand. So that wouldn't work even biblically. ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל,
V'tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, not only that, that's in terms of the
act of giving her the גט. Get. But there's also a question
about her status of being divorced. Because we taught in the house
of
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, ושלחה מביתו, V'shillachah mibeito, she should he should
send her from his house. מי שמשולחת ואינה חוזרת, Mi shemeshullachat v'einah
chozeret, somebody who understood what it means to be sent away, that
she's sent away and she doesn't come back.
יצתה זו שמשולחת וחוזרת, Yatzta zo shemeshullachat v'chozeret, as opposed to somebody
who doesn't even understand that they've been divorced. So that's actually a
very interesting different story, right? It's not just the ability to physically
do the act and define it that it's in my control, but
it's to understand what the status of being divorced means. So it
might be that you don't need a בר דעת, Bar da'as, could
be a קטנה, Ktanah, could be whatever, but somebody at least has
to understand that they are divorced. It's quite fascinating. If they can't
understand even though she's passive in the act, like if she was
active, you would totally understand it. How could you sell something or
buy something if you don't understand what that transaction is that you're
engaging in? What it means to divest yourself of property, what it
means to acquire property? But even though it's basically unilateral and against
her will, if she doesn't understand what the status is that is
being imposed on her, then she is not divorced. Well, let's just
finish it, hold on, you'll ask me a question in a second.
So לא צריכא דיודעת לשמור גיטה ואינה יודעת לשמור עצמה. Lo, tzricha
d'yada lishmor gitah v'einah yada lishmor atzmah.
So
right, the obvious answer: she's at a state where she can protect
what's put in her hand and she understands well enough that she's
been divorced, but she can't protect
herself. And therefore it's basically only a rabbinic problem at this stage,
not a biblical.
Let's just get to the תוספתא. Tosefta. ואינה יודעת לשמור עצמה, ve-einah
yoda’at lishmor atzmah, דבר תורה, dvar Torah, שוטה מתגרשת. shotah mitgareshet. יודעת
לשמור גיטה, yoda'at lishmor gittah, that she knows to watch her get
and also what's not being said is and she also understands what
it means to be divorced. Maybe that's part of יודעת yoda’at watching
her get that she understands the importance of it. But anyway, ואמרו
רבנן ve-amru Rabbanan and the rabbis say לא תפקה, lo tifkah,
she cannot be divorced, שלא ינהגו בה מנהג הפקר she-lo yinhagu bah
minhag hefker that she should not be treated taken advantage of. אמר
רב אידי Amar Rav Idi נמי דקתני nami de-ktani that could also
be inferred from the language of the Mishnah, because it says דתני
לדידה de-tani l'didah נשתטת nishtatet when she becomes a שוטה shotah לא
יוציא, lo yotzi,
he shall not divorce her. וגבי דידי ve-gabei didey when he becomes
a שוטה shotah or חרש, cheresh, לא יוציא עולמית, lo yotzi olamit,
may never divorce her. מה שנא הכא דקתני עולמית ומה שנא התם
דלא קתני עולמית? mah shnah hacha de-ktanid olamit u-mah shnah hatam de-lo
ktanid olamit? Why when he is the שוטה shotah it says never,
and when she is the שוטה shotah it does not say never?
אלא שמע מינה ella shma minah דאורייתא de-Oraita דרבנן. de-Rabbanan.
The difference is that in his case when he's a שוטה shotah
or חרש, cheresh, biblically it won't work, even if he does it
it won't work. So that's why it said he can never work,
he's out of the פרשה. parsha. When she is the one that's
a שוטה, shotah, biblically it does work, but we're not allowing it.
So it doesn't use the word עולמית olamit to tell you it's
not allowed, but not that בדיעבד bediavad it would not be effective.
Yes, Michael?
So my question is this, I mean with the קטן katan or
קטנה ktanah I should really say, like, you know because you can
actually do קידושין kiddushin if she's three years old, right? And you
can still divorce her, right?
Could be even less than three years old.
Right, so I don't understand, I mean like you know she won't
understand.
No, so the difference is, ah, so the difference is A, first
of all there could be a קטנה ktanah that's of the age
that she does understand, right? How old is she? Ten, nine, eight,
whatever? But if she's very young you're right, but then her father
would be the one representing her side and that actually and then
you'd give the get to the father and that actually leads to
an interesting question that תוספות Tosafot has, which is what would be
the story about a שוטה shotah if she was still a קטנה
ktanah and the father got the get and that's what this long
תוספות Tosafot is about. Okay, איבעיא להו. iba'u lehu. They ask the
following question. אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri.
I think it tells us the answer.
Right, said רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. What do
you expect, there's two opinions. Said רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri,
so he says what's the difference between when the איש ish is
the חרש cheresh and the אשה isha is the חרשת chereshet and
the answer is the difference is that an אשה isha is divorced
against her will, so even if she's a חרשת. chereshet. איבעיא להו.
iba'u lehu. So that's the question. רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri, איש פשיטא ליה, ish pshita lei, is it obvious to
him that a man who's a חרש cheresh cannot divorce his wife,
ואשה קא מבעיא ליה, ve-isha ka miba'u lei, he wants to know
why can't a woman therefore, why is a woman able to be
divorced if a man can't? או דילמא odilma or is it the
opposite? אשה פשיטא ליה, isha pshita lei, it's obvious to him that
a woman can be divorced if she's a חרשת, chereshet, ואיש קא
מבעיא ליה, ve-ish ka miba'u lei, and he wants to know why
isn't a man like the woman? Is he saying why isn't the
man like the woman or why isn't the woman like the man?
Of course it's possible he doesn't know which is which, he just
says why aren't they the same? תא שמע, ta shma, מדקאמרו ליה,
mi-de-ka'amru lei, they said to him, אינו דומה איש מגרש לאשה מתגרשת,
eino domeh ish m'garesh l'isha mitgereshet, the man divorcing man is not
like the woman being divorced, שהאשה יוצאה
לרצונה ושלא לרצונה, she-isha yotza l'ratzonah ve-she-lo l'ratzonah, woman is divorced against
her will, willingly and unwillingly, ואיש אינו מוציא אלא לרצונו, ve-ish eino
motzi ela l'ratzono, and a man only willingly. So since they end
by saying this the man is only willingly, it seems like they're
trying to prove a point about the man. שמע מינה, shma mina,
איש קא מבעיא ליה, ish ka miba'u lei,
you see that his question is why can't the man be a
חרש cheresh if the woman can be a חרשת. chereshet. אדרבה adaraba
the opposite. מדקאמרו ליה אף זו כיוצא בה, mi-de-ka'amru lei af zu
ke-yotze bah,
since at the end of that saying they bring the story you
know about the רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada and
the case about the קטנה ktanah that was married by her father
and they say this woman, this חרשת chereshet is like the קטנה.
ktanah. So you see שמע מינה, shma mina, right that was רבי
יוחנן בן גודגדא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada, no, חרשת chereshet that was
married by her father, anyway. So you see that he's trying to
prove the question about the story of the woman. שמע מינה, shma
mina, אשה קא מבעיא ליה, isha ka miba'u lei, the question was
why is the woman able to be divorced if she's a חרשת.
chereshet. אלא ella says the גמרא, Gemara, רבי יוחנן בן נורי לדבריהם
קאמר. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri le-divrehem ka’amar.
He's saying according to the Rabbis. לדידי l'didi as far as I'm
concerned, כי היכי דאיש לא מצי מגרש אשה לא מצי מתגרשת. ke-hecha
de-ish lo matzi m'garesh isha lo matzi mitgareshet.
The same way a man can't, a woman cannot divorce if he's
a חרש, cheresh, a woman can't be divorced. אלא לדידכו ella le-didchu
but according to you, מה שנא אשה ומה שנא איש? mah shnah
isha u-mah shnah ish? What's the difference between a man and a
woman? So meaning the way the גמרא Gemara answers it is sort
of what I said. It's not like he doesn't understand the case
of the man or he doesn't understand the case of the woman.
He's challenging them on the inconsistency. He says as far as I'm
concerned neither of them can do it. But as far as you're
concerned explain the inconsistency. And since he's saying explain the inconsistency, they're
going to explain both why the man cannot and why the woman
can. Okay? So therefore מה שני ומה שני? mah shnai u-mah shnai?
מה שני איש, mah shnai ish, אמרו ליה אינו דומה איש מגרש
לאשה מתגרשת amru lei eino domeh ish m'garesh l'isha mitgereshet and then
they say no, here's why it is not inconsistent, the man has
to be an actor in the process, he cannot be a חרש,
cheresh, the woman is not an actor, she can be a חרשת.
chereshet. Yes?
Where is the סוגיא sugya if I remember correctly in קידושין kiddushin
in which the גמרא Gemara makes a comparison of קידושין kiddushin and
גיטין, Gittin, one is not בעל כרחו...
bal korcho... ויצאה והיתה ve-yatz’ah ve-haitah in the beginning, yeah. Yeah, there
are some ways in which they're similar but the בעל כרחו bal
korcho is obviously the huge place where they're different. So I mean
it's the סוגיא sugya in the beginning you have קידושין, kiddushin, right,
that you need to be דעת, da'at, right,
which is... By the way, important because as far as the תורה
*Torah* is concerned, you never have the woman, I mean other than
the רבקה *Rivka* story, but you never have the woman, willingly agree,
she's always being married off by her father. The very fact that
the חז"ל *Chazal* understand that there are cases in which the woman
is outside of her father's control, that she's an adult and that
she decides on her own whether to be married is not in
the פסוקים *psukim*. So they're reading all the פסוקים *psukim* as a
case of a minor, but the פסוקים *psukim* never give you an
example, I mean it's not just in the תורה *Torah*, I don't
think in any of the stories in all of תנ"ך *Tanach* you
have an example where a woman is marrying herself.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. But yes, I
mean that's the point, in some ways they're parallel, but in the
issue of דעת *da'at* they're different. העיד רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא *Heid
Rabi Yochanan ben Gudgada*. רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא *Rabi Yochanan ben Gudgada*
testified about the case about a חרשת chereshes *chereshet* married by the
father that it was binding דאורייתא d'oraisas. *d'oreita* and then she can
be divorced. Okay. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, says said רבא *Rava*, מעדותו
של רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא *me'eduto shel Rabi Yochanan ben Gudgada*, from
his testimony that a woman does not have to be sort of
a בר דעת bar da'as. *bar da'at* in the גירושין *geirushin* process,
we would say the following. אמר לעדים *Amar l'eidim*, if a man
says to witnesses, ראו גט get זה שאני נותן *re'u get zeh
sh'ani noten*, see this גט get *get* I'm about to give my
wife, he shows it to them, they read it, they see it's
a גט get. *get*, he puts it in an envelope, ואמר לה
כנסי שטר חוב זה *v'amar lah kinsi shtar chov zeh*, when he
gives it to her, it's sort of like serving a summons or
whatever, you trick the person into accepting it, he says, here take
this
IOU document.
And then she takes it, and then ah see haha got you
you've been served or whatever, it's a גט get *get*. So הרי
זו מגורשת *harei zo megureshet*, it works, because you don't need her
דעת *da'at* in the process. Okay, so in the same way she
has an absence of דעת *da'at* it works, if she's also being
deceived it also works. מי לא אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
בן גודגדא לא בעינן דעתה *Mi lo amar Rabi Yochanan ben Gudgada
lo beinan da'atah*, didn't רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא *Rabi Yochanan ben Gudgada*
say you don't need her דעת *da'at*, הכא נמי לא בעינן דעתה
*hacha nami lo beinan da'atah*, here too you don't need her דעת
*da'at*. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says פשיטא *peshita*, isn't that obvious? No. מהו
דתימא *Ma'u d'teima*, I might have thought מדאמר לה כנסי שטר חוב
זה בטליה *mi d'amar lah kinsi shtar chov zeh batlei*, since he's
describing it as a writ of debt, not as a writ of
divorce, maybe that act should be seen as negating the גט get.
*get* because there's an idea that the husband can be מבטל *mevatel*
a גט get *get*, okay that's a thing we'll see when we
get to גיטין *Gittin*. So maybe this should be interpreted as an
act of ביטול *bittul* of nullifying the גט get, *get*. קא משמע
לן *Kamashma l'an*, to this is teaching you, אי איתא דבטליה *i'ita
d'batlei*, if he had really nullified it, לעדים הוה אמר להו *l'eidim
hava amar lehu*, he would tell the witnesses that he had been
nullifying it because he made a point of telling the witnesses that
it was a גט get, *get*. ומדלא אמר לעדים *U'mi d'lo amar
l'eidim*, since he didn't tell that to the witnesses, לא בטליה *lo
batlei* he did not nullify it ולא מידי miyadai, *v'lo miday* at
all. והאי דקאמר הכי *V'hai d'ka'amar hachi*, why did he call it
a writ of debt? מחמת כיסופא הוא דקאמר לה *Machamat kisufa hu
d'ka'amar lah* or להו *lehu*, he was saying it because he was
embarrassed to say to her face that he was divorcing her. Now
of course there is a חידוש *chidush* because since we said before
that part of the idea is that she has to be משלחת
ואינה חוזרת *mishalachat v'eina chozeret*, she has to be of a state
that she knows what it means to be divorced, you might think
that when he gives it to her he has to inform her
of her status, that she's being divorced, right? Because even in the
other cases you had a case of חרשת chereshes, *chereshet* or whatever,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* got to saying that that would only work
by somebody who knew they were being divorced, right? Remember we said
that before? Right, remember? So even with all the cases of קטן
Katan, וחרשת *katan v'chereshet* etc., so maybe if she doesn't know it
wouldn't work. So it seems like the גמרא Gemara? *Gemara's* understanding that
as long as she is a type of a person who could
understand what being divorced means, even if she was not aware of
it at the moment when she was given the גט *get*, the
moment she was given the גט *get* she was tricked, nevertheless if
she is the גברא *gavra*, right, of a mental state that she
will understand what being divorced means, it's not that that has to
be clear at the time of the delivery. So there seems to
be even a bigger חידוש *chidush* here than that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is dealing with about what this idea of משלחת ואינה חוזרת
*mishalachat v'eina chozeret* is. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues, and
now till the end of this פרק perek. *perek* we're going to
enter into a fun and classic סוגיא sugya *sugya* which you're not
even going to understand what it has to do with anything we've
been talking about until it gets to the very end where it
ties in a piece of our משנה mishna. *Mishnah* into the discussion,
and this is the major locus of the locus classicus of the
discussion in ש"ס *Shas* of the סוגיא sugya. *sugya* called קטן אוכל
נבלות katan ochel neveilos בית דין Beis Din מצווין להפרישו או לא
*katan ochel nevelot bei dina metzuvan l'hafrisho o lo*. If a minor
is eating traif food, is the בית דין Beis Din *Beit Din*
obligated to intervene? What is the communal responsibility represented by the בית
דין Beis Din *Beit Din* to prevent minors from doing sins? This
is not the question of the parents, that's an issue of חינוך
chinuch *chinuch* and that's a whole discussion the ראשונים *Rishonim* have because
interestingly חינוך chinuch *chinuch* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* primarily comes up
with parents training kids. A father, first of all there's an interesting
question whether חינוך chinuch *chinuch* applies to the mother believe it or
not. But anyway it primarily comes up with the father training his
child, primarily his son to do מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot*, to put on
תפילין *tefillin*, to take לולב *lulav*, you know that's where ציצית *tzitzit*,
right, right, that's where you get the emphasis of חינוך Chinuch, *chinuch*,
you do not get an emphasis of חינוך Chinuch *chinuch* in terms
of preventing from doing transgressions, okay? But let's even assume that that's
included, although some ראשונים *Rishonim* say interestingly that it's not, חינוך Chinuch
*chinuch* somehow is only on positive מצוות *mitzvot* not on negative, I
don't really understand that but that's certainly where the evidence points. Anyway,
but bracketing חינוך *chinuch*, maybe parents of course do have a responsibility
to... intervene, but the question is not parents. The question is the
community's responsibility. Do they have one to prevent minors from sinning? And
that is going to be the question we're going to have and
we're going to see in the end of the סוגיא how it
ties into our משנה. mishna. Yes.
I would think like more than the parents, isn't there in some
sense like an understanding of the father being חייב? chayav?
Like for oh, you mean like the ברוך שפטרני Baruch Shepatrani thing.
Yeah, so that's an interesting philosophical question. But more הלכתית, halachically, it's
really more about חינוך as opposed to like, it's true like when
we say that ברכה bracha of ברוך שפטרני, Baruch Shepatrani, you get
the עבירות. aveiros. But interestingly, you know that type of more metaphysical
understanding is not like הלכה. halacha. The הלכתי halachic language is whether
you're חייב chayav in חינוך or not. Okay, you know but it's
a good point, you know which is, is it considered when a
minor does a עבירה aveira or when a minor does a מצוה,
mitzvah, is it like there was an עבירה aveira done but nobody
is liable for it? Or and then maybe there well maybe the
father's liable for it? Is it like an עבירה aveira wasn't done
at all? Is it a מצוה mitzvah was done but it doesn't,
right? So like some interesting questions would be like there's a whole
big רב חיים Rav Chaim on the issue of if a minor
brings a קרבן פסח korban Pesach on פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon and
then he becomes an adult between פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon and פסח
שני, Pesach Sheni, does he have to bring a פסח שני? Pesach
Sheni? Maybe it was already like he brought a קרבן פסח, korban
Pesach, you know, he brought it as a minor, right? If somebody
starts counting ספירת העומר, Sefiras HaOmer, this happens a good 15 percent
of the time that somebody becomes בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah or בת
מצוה, Bat Mitzvah, you know, in the middle of ספירה. Sefirah. So
does the beginning of the counting count as a מצוה mitzvah that
you can continue to count with a ברכה bracha when you become
בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah in the middle. Okay, so anyway there's all
those interesting questions. Anyway, so partly you're right. If it's considered an
עבירה aveira but maybe nobody's being blamed for it, well maybe the
metaphysical reality of it being an עבירה aveira requires בית דין Beis
Din to intervene. Okay, but maybe it's not, or maybe it's just
a type of a communal חינוך type of a responsibility, you know,
or maybe as a community are we allowed to tolerate it? By
not doing anything we're tacitly allowing, you know, this and that affects
our character as a community. So there's a lot of interesting questions.
This is the סוגיא of קטן אוכל נבלות katan ochel neveilos, and
we will again see at the end how it ties in to
our משנה. Mishnah So let's take a look at the bottom of
קיג Kuf Yud Gimmel עמוד ב. Amud B. Okay, רב
יצחק בר ביסנא,
Rav Yitzchak bar
Bisna, two lines from the bottom. רב יצחק בר ביסנא אירכסו ליה
מפתחי דבי מדרשא ברשות הרבים. Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna irchesu lei maftechei
de'vei midrasha birshus harabbim. He lost the keys to the בית המדרש
Beis HaMedrash in the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. I guess before שבת,
Shabbos, okay? And now they everybody had to get into the בית
המדרש Beis HaMedrash on שבת Shabbos and I mean they're not so
lost, he knows where they are, but they're in the middle of
the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. How's he going to open up the
בית מדרש? Beis Medrash? בשבתא, beshabata, on שבת. Shabbos.
So אתא לקמיה דרבי
פדת.
ata lekamei
de'Rabbi Padas.
All right, well let's see what רבי פדת Rabbi Padas says. אתא
לקמיה דרבי פדת, אמר ליה זיל דבר טלי וטליא, ata lekamei de'Rabbi
Padas, amar lei zil davar tali v'talya,
go take a young טלי וטליא tali v'talya our kid, like a
kid goat, but it also means like we say a kid. Go
take a kid, go take a small boy or girl. וליטיילו התם,
v'litaylu hasam, and go take a walk in the רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim ואי משכחו להו, v'ei meshkachu lehu, and then if they find
the keys מייתו להו, maisu lehu, they'll bring it and they'll say
Daddy, look what I found, I found these keys. So therefore, you
know, make it like sort of like when you say like oh
my god I accidentally turned off your light, here I have the
baby play near the light switch and maybe he'll accidentally turn it
on, okay? So have some kids play in the park and then
you wait by the door, you wait by the front door of
the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, and if they find the keys they'll
say oh look what I found. Okay, אלמא קסבר, alma kasavar, so
you see he's of the opinion קטן Katan אוכל נבלות, neveilos, interesting
that the classic way it describes a scenario of does בית דין
Beis Din have to intervene or do we, anybody not the parents,
have to intervene is by eating tref food. If a minor is
eating נבלות, אין בית דין מצווין להפרישו, ein Beis Din metzuving lehafrisho,
בית דין Beis Din is not commanded to make him to, you
know, intervene, to separate him from it. And not only that, here
they can even, you know, allow it to happen or you know
or construct it. Yeah, I know, I know, it's even worse here.
Anyway.
I don't know, we're not in הלכות שבת. hilchos Shabbos. לימא מסייע
ליה, lima mesayei lei,
let's see if we can support this. לא יאמר אדם לתינוק הבא
לי מפתח הבא לי חותם, lo yomar adam letinok hava li mafteach
hava li chosam, a person cannot say to a minor bring me
my key or bring me a seal on שבת, Shabbos, אלא מניחו
אוכל ומניחו זורק, ela manicho ochel u'manicho zorek, but you're allowed to
leave him, you know, if he's like tearing up grass or throwing
things into the public domain, you don't have to stop him, but
you're not allowed to tell him to do it. So you see
exactly this. You cannot tell a kid to do an עבירה, aveira,
but you don't have to stop it. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר אביי תולש בעציץ שאינו נקוב וזורק בכרמלית דרבנן. amar Abaye tolesh
be'atzitz she'eino nakuv v'zorek be'karmelis d'rabbanan. Well, maybe that's only דרבנן d'rabbanan
עבירות. aveiros. Maybe he's pulling out plants from a pot that doesn't
have a hole in it, isn't connected to the ground. Maybe he's
only throwing in a כרמלית, karmelis, not in a רשות הרבים. reshus
harabbim. So maybe you don't have to we can concede that you
don't have to intervene for דרבנן. d'rabbanans. Our question is whether you
have to intervene for דאורייתא. de'oraysa And of course the case again
by שבת Shabbos and רשות הרבים reshus harabbim wasn't just lack of
intervention, it was even about you know about creating it so that
it would happen. So that's the question on the table. תא שמע,
ta shma, עובדי כוכבים שבא לכבות, ovdei kochavim she'ba lechabos, there's a
fire and a non-Jew comes to try to put out the fire,
אין אומרים לו כבה ואל תכבה, ein omrim lo kabeh v'al techabeh,
you're not allowed to tell him put it out, because that would
be an אמירה לנכרי amira lenochri on שבת. Shabbos. But on the
other hand, you don't have to tell him don't put it
out, מפני שאין שביתתו עליהם, mipnei she'ein shevisaso aleihem,
you don't have any responsibility to make sure that a גוי goy
keeps שבת. Shabbos. קטן katan הבא לכבות *katan ha-ba le-khabot*, if the
minor comes to put it out, אומרים לו אל תכבה *omrim lo
al tikhbe*, you have to say don't put it out. ששביתתו עליהם
*she-shevisato aleihem*, because the you're you're obligated to make sure that your
kid keeps שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, so here you see very clearly that
a father has at least, well, it doesn't say a father, קטן
*katan*, that the other people have a responsibility to make sure kids
don't violate שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*. This seems to prove against our point
that you are obligated. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רבי
יוחנן באותו דעת אביו Aviv. *amar Rabbi Yochanan be-oso da'as aviv*, oh,
no, this is different. This is the reason you have to intervene
is because when the קטן *katan*, when the minor's putting out a
fire, it's not like he's doing it for himself. What, he just
enjoys putting out fires? No, it's because he knows that his father
wants him to do it and maybe he's always looking back at
his father and making sure that his father's happy with what he's
doing. So that's a type of if not an explicit אמירה Amira.
*amira*, not explicitly telling your kid to do it, but it's a
type of a case of implicitly he's doing it as as for
you. And therefore that's why it would be problematic. Now the case
of finding the keys in רשות הרבים reshut harabim *reshus ha-rabim* is
he wasn't doing it for you. He just said "Daddy, look what
I found, these shiny keys." Okay, he's showing it to you, but
he's not doing it for you. Whereas in this case, he actually
is doing it for the father and that makes it problematic. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, דכוותיה גבי עובד כוכבים דעושה
על דעת ישראל *dikhvashei gabei oveid kokhavim de-osei al da'as Yisrael*, one
minute, so if it was the non-Jew in a parallel case, that
he was doing it because he knew that his friend the Jew
wanted him to put out the fire, מי שרי *mi sharei*, that
wouldn't be allowed? So it's not really a difference of a Jew
and a non-Jew, of a non-Jew and a minor, right? Because a
non-Jew is also forbidden if he's doing it for the sake of
his friend the Jew. עובד כוכבים... so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
no, עובד כוכבים אדעתא דנפשיה adata denafshei? עביד *oveid kokhavim ada'ata de-nafshei
avid*. That's exactly the point. That if a non-Jew does it, he's
always doing it, you know, for his own concerns. Like even if
he's doing it because he knows you his friend will like it,
he figures, well, then maybe he'll be nicer to me, maybe he'll
pay me for it. So even if he's doing it for you,
it's like, you know, it's also for himself, it's basically for himself.
It's a question of like what's his own self-interest in doing something
that that will be good for you. Whereas by the minor, you
know, the minor's doing it fundamentally...
basically the non-Jew's only doing it for his own interest. What?
I understand, he is doing it for his own interest and that
makes it okay. Whereas by the minor, the minor is basically doing
it, he's not thinking about what am I going to get out,
I mean, you could say, well, I want my daddy to like
it, and that's, you know, whatever, but anyway, somehow the minor's seen
as much more fundamentally because he's a minor and not an adult,
as fundamentally doing it just to make you happy. And therefore it's
seen as an extension of you. Now, the issue here that should
be pointed out is two things, number is well one thing primarily,
which is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sees this question of do you
have to intervene by the case of the minor on שבת Shabbos,
*Shabbos* as part of a general question of do you have to
intervene if a minor is doing something right, is doing an עבירה
aveira. *aveira*. But the difference is, the language of the משנה *Mishnah*
that it quoted or the ברייתא Baraisa *Beraysa*, I forget, is שביתתו
עליך *shevisato alecha*,
that his observing of שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* is your responsibility, which is
a unique שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* idea. There is like a פסוק *pasuk*
in the עשרת הדברות *Aseres ha-Dibros*, which is right, בנך ובתך עבדך
ואמתך וחמורך למען ינוח *binkha u-viskha avdekha va-amasekha khamorkha le-maan yanua'ach*, right,
you have a responsibility to make sure that your whole family including
your minor children are observing שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. So it's actually interesting
that this גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* seems to ignore this. This גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* seems that the only difference between a minor and a non-Jew
is that a minor does it totally for you and the non-Jew
does it, you know, for himself. And that but basically the problem
of the minor doing it is like it's an extension of you,
it's like you told him to do it, it's like you wanted
him to do it. Why should that be the problem by the
minor? The minor problem is because you have an obligation to make
sure that your kids don't violate שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. It's a unique
שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* idea, right? It says למען ינוח *le-maan yanua'ach*, you
know, שורך וחמורך וכל *shorkha va-khamorkha va-khol*, whatever, whatever the פסוק *pasuk*
is, you know, בנך ובתך שורך וחמורך וכל בהמתך *binkha u-viskha shorkha
va-khamorkha va-khol behmatekha*.
Exactly. So what's interesting is because of this סוגיא *sugya* I have
to tell you here's a fascinating little point, which is the biblical
מצוה *mitzvah* of making sure that your kids keep שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*,
right, it's in the עשרת הדברות *Aseres ha-Dibros* it occurs a few
times, barely exists in the halakhic literature. Because when it the one
place where it exists is this case here by the fire and
by the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* deals with it, it's being
interpreted as nothing unique about it being your kid and it being
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. It's all just about whether he's doing it for
you or not for you. So the idea that there's a special
מצוה *mitzvah* on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* to make sure that your kids
observe שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, you know, it's later אחרונים acharonim, *achronim* say,
oh wait, maybe here this is because there's a biblical מצוה *mitzvah*
to make sure your kids keep שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. But that's not
you don't get that sense in this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* at all.
In this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* you get a sense it's almost like
a type of an אמירה לגוי *amira le-goy*, that the only difference
of your kid doing it and a non-Jew doing it is whether
the non-Jew's doing it for himself and a kid is doing it
for you, but not like there's a special responsibility in terms of
your kid.
Yeah, is there some connection between the idolaters also doing it to
please the Jew because if he thought the Jew would be displeased
he wouldn't do it?
Right, so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, that even though
he's doing it to please the Jew, he's ultimately doing it for
his own self-interest.
The motivation.
And child too in a way, you know?
Yes, you'd have that too. Why do you want your daddy to
be happy with you, your mommy? Because you want the positive feedback
and whatever, but the גמרא Gemara is still saying, which is reasonable,
which is that a minor is still much more seen as like
an extension, dependent and an extension than a person. But again, the
interesting thing is, is that the גמרא Gemara makes the whole issue
here, you know, because of like it's a specific context that he's
doing it for your sake, does not create a special obligation on
שבת Shabbos in terms of making sure that your kids keep שבת.
Shabbos. And the big difference is, it's one thing if it's somebody
else's kid, right? The ברייתא Baraisa just said קטן, the גמרא Gemara.
introduced the idea of אביו. If it's somebody else's kids, you could
say, oh well, we don't have to intervene if somebody else's kids
is eating טרפות, Treifos, somebody else's kid is violating שבת, Shabbos but
if it's your kid, right, do you have a special obligation in
terms of שבת Shabbos, to make sure they don't violate beyond anything
that's being discussed in this גמרא? Gemara Yes, Michael.
So that's what maybe I wasn't clear before, maybe I just misunderstood
something. The conclusion of the גמרא Gemara is that אב קא עביד
אדעתא דנפשיה. Av ka avid adata denafshei. Right. So why can't you
just tell him then if he's doing אדעתא דנפשיה? adata denafshei. What
do you mean?
It's good that he's doing אדעתא דנפשיה. Therefore your— no, if you
tell him then it's an explicit אמירה. Then you're in the frames,
the fact that what he's doing is seen as an extension of
you.
And then the other question is like, you know, this one it
seems like again, getting back to the פחות פחות pachos pachos thing,
which seems that there was another way to get out of it,
and they let him do— no, no, but the broader question is
in general, like let's say there's a way for you to get
out of it, right, you know, or have the קטן do it,
which is, you know, if you will, like less of an עבירה.
aveirah, Right.
So that's— so you're right, so that's a good question, right, like
you know, which one is, you know. The גמרא Gemara seems to
feel like if you're not מצווה להפרישו, metzuvei l'hafrisho, it's completely not
problematic. But you're right, it's a good question in general when you
have multiple ways of workarounds, which how do you rank them? Okay,
so that, yeah, that's a good question. Fine. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, תא שמע. Ta Shma. So בן חבר,
Ben Chaver, so we're still— our argument is that maybe yes, you
don't have to intervene with rabbinic things, but you do have to
intervene with biblical ones, maybe. And or and the case by שבת
Shabbos, or it's and maybe that's proof by the case of שבת,
Shabbos, or maybe the case of שבת Shabbos. is a special case
because he's doing it אדעתא דאביו. adata d'aviv. Or maybe what I'm
saying is, not just me, later אחרונים, but unfortunately it seems strange
that the גמרא Gemara ignores it, that שבת Shabbos is a special
case because of the parent's obligation in terms of his kids on
שבת. Shabbos Okay, תא שמע. Ta Shma. בן חבר שרגיל לילך אצל
אבי אמו. Ben Chaver sheragil laleches etzel avi imo. The child of
a חבר, chaver, presumably a minor, that normally would go to his
grandfather, his mother's grandfather, עם הארץ. Am ha'aretz. And he's an עם
הארץ, Am ha'aretz, he's not a חבר, chaver, because the assumption is,
is that if the חבר chaver practices are maintained through the father,
they kind of they sort of are shaped paternal lines determine like
the commitment to these חבר chaver practices. So it's the maternal grandfather
that doesn't keep these practices. אין חוששין שמא יאכילנו דברים שאינם מתוקנים.
Ein chosheshin shema ya'achilenu devarim she'einam metukanim. So basically you send your
kid to spend some time with the grandparents and they don't keep
the same level of כשרות Kashrus as you, you don't have to
be concerned with that. ומצא בידו פירות, U'matza beyado peiros, and if
the kid comes home and brings home some fruit that his grandfather
gave him, אין זקוק לו, ein zakuk lo, you don't have to
be concerned with it and say, oh no, don't eat it, we
have to take תרומות ומעשרות. Terumos u'ma'asros. You don't have to worry
about it. אמר רבי יוחנן, בדמאי הקלו. Amar Rabbi Yochanan bedemai hiklu.
So you see? I mean, here's a classic case, right? You send
your kid, you know, your kids go to school and they get
kids' fruit from other kids or whatever it is, right? How much
do you have to intervene? And the גמרא Gemara, sounds like you
don't have to. So if they're under בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, בת
מצוה. Bas Mitzvah. אמר רבי יוחנן בדמאי הקלו. bedemai hiklu.
That's only דמאי, demai, which is questionable whether תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u'ma'asros
were taken and it's a rabbinic issue, so same like we were
saying before, it's a special rabbinic issue. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא טעמא דדמאי. Ela ta'ama d'demai. The reason you don't have to
intervene because it's rabbinic. הא ודאי בעי לאפרושי. Ha vadai ba'i l'afroshei.
If it definitely was, you know, with טבל tevel you would have
to take מעשר. ma'aser. ואמר רבי יוחנן באוכל על דעת אביו? Ve'amar
Rabbi Yochanan b'ochel al da'at aviv? Didn't Rabbi Yochanan give the answer
by the fire that the only reason it was a problem was
because he was doing it for the sake of his father? Which
sounds like Rabbi Yochanan in general would not require intervention. And so
here how is Rabbi Yochanan saying that it's only because it's rabbinic?
What's the story? What's Rabbi Yochanan's position? Do you have to intervene
for biblical or not? Here it sounds like he's saying yes, before
it sounds like he was saying no. So the גמרא Gemara. says,
אלא רבי יוחנן צריכה מיספקא ליה. Ela Rabbi Yochanan tzericha mispaka lei.
Rabbi Yochanan doesn't know. כי הכא מדחי ליה כי הכא מדחי ליה.
Keihacha medachei lei keihacha medachei lei. Either way, he says I can't
prove it this way, I can't prove it that way, there's always
some explanation. Okay, so Rabbi Yochanan isn't hasn't taken a position here,
but you can't prove it from שבת, Shabbos maybe because he's doing
it for the sake of his father. You can't prove it from
this, maybe this is rabbinic, but what exactly is the right answer?
Who knows? Now I should also point out that now we're already
on the second case which seems to involve the father, right? The
case by the fire didn't say in the ברייתא the father, but
Rabbi Yochanan inserted— I think it's actually a משנה— whereas and this
case, sending the kid and the kid coming home from the grandfather's
house, also seems like it's the parents that are involved, and nevertheless
the גמרא gemara. treats it the same way, which seems to be
that even for parents who have an obligation of חינוך,
if בית דין doesn't have to intervene, parents don't have to intervene.
That's the implication of this גמרא, gemara right? Which is pretty shocking.
You should then say, what ever happened to the חינוך obligation? But
it seems like some say for some bizarre reason the חינוך only...
implied by מצות עשה, Mitzvas Asei, not by לא תעשה. Lo Sa'asei.
Why that should be I don't know. Okay, but it's worth pointing
out that we seem to be talking even with the parents involved.
תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in here: is there a difference between...
isn't there a difference between, well I can rely on the fact
that it's probably not טרפה treifa food,
or, you know, because it might well be טרפה treifa but I
don't have an obligation to intervene? Those two...
That's your point, that it's ספק. safek. So that's the... that was
רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's answer. That might be different because it was
ספק. safek. Okay. תא שמע, Ta Shma, בן חבר כהן שרגיל לילך
אצל אבי אמו כהן עם הארץ. ben chaver Kohen she'ragil leileich eitzel
avi imo Kohen am ha'aretz. So now again if the child of
a חבר chaver Kohen who goes to his maternal grandfather who actually
also happens to be a Kohen, why I don't know, you could
have said maternal grandfather isn't a Kohen, right, because it's maternal. But
no, he's a כהן עם הארץ. Kohen am ha'aretz. So here it's
a different concern, not just דמאי, demai, but תרומה טמאה, terumah tmeiah,
which is a biblical problem. Okay, so in that case אין חוששין
שמא יאכילנו תרומה טמאה, ein chosheshin shema ya'achileinu terumah tmeiah, you're not
afraid that he'll give him תרומה terumah that is טמאה. tmeiah. מצא
בידו פירות אין זקוק לו, Matza beyado peiros ein zakuk lo, he
brings home... you don't have to worry about food, you don't have
to worry about it. So that's a real דאורייתא de'oraysa concern. So
the גמרא gemara says
בתרומה דרבנן, bi'terumah d'rabbanan, rabbinic תרומה, terumah, like either nowadays or fruit
as opposed to grains. תא שמע, Ta Shma, so again yes a
lot of evidence that you don't have to intervene, but we're saying
it's all rabbinic. It's all rabbinic sin. תא שמע, Ta Shma, יונק
תינוק והולך מעובדת כוכבים, Yoneik tinok v'holeich mei'ovedes kochavim, an infant can
go ahead and nurse from a non-Jewish woman
as opposed to the משה Moshe story. ובהמה טמאה, u'beheimah tmeiah,
and actually from a non-kosher animal, right? Bizarre, like, you know, I
don't know if it means directly, I mean the גמרא gemara will
actually give us a case of it directly. Okay. Give him pig
milk or something. ואין חוששין ביונק שקץ, ve'ein chosheshin b'yoneik sheketz, and
you're not concerned, 'oh my god he's eating this, you know, abominable,
nursing this abominable stuff'. ולא יאכילנו נבלות וטרפות, V'lo ya'achileinu neveilos u'treifos,
but do not directly feed him טרפה treifa food. שקצים ורמשים, Shekatzim
u'remashim, or like these creepy crawlies. ומכולן יונק מהן ואפילו בשבת, U'mikulan
yoneik meihen v'afilu b'Shabbos, and he can directly nurse from them even
on שבת. Shabbos. ובגדול אסור, u'begadol assur, and by an adult it's
forbidden to directly, you know, suck from the animal. אבא שאול אומר
נוהגים היינו שיונקין מבהמה טהורה ביום טוב, Abba Shaul omer nohagim hayinu
she'yonkin m'beheimah tehorah b'Yom Tov,
very bizarre. We would directly suck, you know, as adults from the,
you know, from a kosher animal... yeah
exactly, milk fresh from the tap on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
we'll discuss the whole thing about milking on שבת Shabbos. and יום
טוב Yom Tov in a minute. But קתני מיהת... katani miyas... The
איסור? issur?
קתני מיהת אין חוששין ביונק שקץ, Katani miyas ein chosheshin b'yoneik sheketz,
you're not concerned that he's going to be eating this טריפה treifa
stuff. So you're not allowed to directly do it, it says לא
יאכילנו, lo ya'achileinu, don't directly feed him, but if he's going ahead
and doing it you don't have to intervene. So the גמרא gemara
says התם משום סכנה, hatam mishum sakana, no, that's because for an
infant to get milk it's a סכנה sakana and that's why we
don't intervene. So the גמרא gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi, he
needs the milk. אי הכי גדול נמי, Ei hachi gadol nami, so
why should a גדול gadol not be allowed to do it? So
the גמרא Gemara says what are you talking about? גדול באומדנא, Gadol
b'umdana, an adult if he's really like starving and he needs it
you would need the doctors, you need to assess it, you couldn't
by default assume, assume that oh my god it's a סכנה. sakana.
גמרא Gemara says קטן נמי ליבעי אומדנא, katan nami liv'ei umdana, why
not also need to evaluate a minor? אמר רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע סתם תינוק מסוכן אצל חלב. Amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua
stam tinok mesukan eitzel chalav. Without any evaluation we say that an
infant needs milk and that's even a concern of סכנה sakana for
milk for an infant. And therefore the basically is saying is that,
yeah, normally we would maybe have to intervene, but we don't... but
we don't... but we don't intervene here because we assume that it
is a... that we assume that it's a health issue. Now I
should say that that line, yes, that line is very important because
actually very relevant to this about... about, you know, nursing and so
on. The whole question comes up about
expressing milk for infants on
שבת, you know, and on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and other types
of cases, and do you allow to do it? So there's a
whole debate whether for a woman to actually manually express milk is
a דאורייתא de'oraysa. of, you know, of like דש dash and סוחט,
socheit, like you know separating out as it were the milk from
the body and so on. That's a problem about... about like threshing,
sort of separating out the grain from the husk. That's the category
of מלאכה melacha it goes under. We'll see that in a minute.
And if you... so there's a whole discussion which we're actually going
to get to in one minute right now in the גמרא Gemara
whether it's דאורייתא. de'oraysa, But if you assume that it might be
דאורייתא, de-oraisa. how are you allowed to do it? And some פוסקים
poskim say, well, you can't, and if a woman needs to do
it in order, you know, maybe they talk about doing it by...
by a גרמא grama and attaching it to a machine on a
timer and so on. But would you allow it to be done
directly? And some פוסקים, poskim, the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer says yes,
because you if you need it for your infant, even if you
need it not this second but you need to store up the
milk so that it's available, you know, then... and... and there's... and
you won't have enough if you don't or you might not have
enough or there's some concern, then yeah then it's a סכנה sakana
issue and you're allowed to do it. So the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz
Eliezer is very lenient when it comes to issues relating to making
sure that... make... yeah, ציץ אליעזר, Tzitz Eliezer, yeah. But he feels
mother's milk is whatever, you know. So anyway so that becomes a
very important discussion in הלכה halacha issues around nursing mothers and שבת
and so on. about how much do
you say, yeah, anything that's done to protect for the sake of
the mother's milk is, you know, is like in the סכנה sakana
category. So within that, relevant to that, let's see the next line
in the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא's Gemara now going to digress and
discuss this nursing thing before it finishes up its discussion about intervening
for עבירות. aveiros. אבא שאול נוהגים היינו שיונקים מבהמה טהורה ביום טוב.
Abba Shaul nohagim hayinu she-yonkim mi-beheima tehorah be-Yom Tov. We would directly
nurse, suckle from the, from kosher animals on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי דאיכא סכנה, Ei de-ika
sakana, if it was some case that people was like, and I
don't know that there was some famine or whatever and it was
a סכנה, sakana, אפילו בשבת נמי, afillu be-Shabbos nami, we should allow
it on שבת. ואי דליכא סכנה, Ve-ei de-leika sakana, if there's no
danger, אפילו ביום טוב אסור, afillu be-Yom Tov assur, it should be
forbidden on יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא צריכא דאיכא צער, lo tzricha de-ika tzaar, you need it, דאיכא
צער, de-ika tzaar, that it was in a middle category. Not a
סכנה, sakana, but a case of, of like, anguish. קסבר מפרק כלאחר
יד היא, Kasavar mesfarek ke-lachar yad hi, directly suckling from an animal
is מפרק. mesfarek. מפרק Mesfarek is separating, it's like דש, dosh,
it's like squeezing out the juice of a lemon. So this is
an unusual way to get the milk out of an animal by
directly suckling from it, so it's only דרבנן, de-rabbanan, you know, it's
a שינוי. shinui. שבת דאיסור סקילה גזרו בה רבנן, Shabbos de-issur sekilah
gazru beh rabbanan, שבת which is a weighty איסור, issur, the רבנן
rabbanan forbade if just in a place of צער. tzaar. יום טוב
דאיסור לאו לא גזרו ביה רבנן, Yom Tov de-issur lav lo gazru
bei rabbanan, יום טוב Yom Tov which is a לאו lav and
it's not punishable by execution like it's not חייב מיתה, chayav misa,
so there the רבנן rabbanan did not prohibit it in the case
of צער tzaar and allowed to do it with a שינוי. shinui.
So this raises a whole lot of questions about because תוספות Tosafot
says, you know, if you look at this תוספות שבת דאיסור סקילה,
Tosafot Shabbos de-issur sekilah, תוספות Tosafot says קשיא, kashya, דאמרינן בפרק אף
על פי, de-amrinan be-perek Af Al Pi, יונק חלב בשבת, yonech chalev
be-Shabbos, דקסבר מפרק כלאחר יד הוא ומשום צער לא גזרו רבנן. de-kasavar
mesfarek ke-lachar yad hu u-mishum tzaar lo gazru rabbanan. Exactly this case
where the גמרא Gemara basically says that you can nurse directly, suckle
directly from an animal because of צער tzaar and they didn't and
you're allowed to do it on שבת, even on שבת, because it's
only a שינוי shinui and it's a דרבנן. de-rabbanan. So there's a
whole question about what degree of, you know, of necessity, מצטער
miztaer
and חולה choleh and all these types of cases is needed to
allow one to do a דרבנן de-rabbanan on שבת, right? So this
גמרא Gemara seems to say well there's a lower threshold for יום
טוב Yom Tov than שבת. Other גמרות Gemoras seem to say that
exactly in this case you're allowed to do these types of things
on שבת if it's a concern of צער. tzaar. So there is
that general question about what type of threshold is needed in order
to allow things, and תוספות Tosafot makes distinctions between חולה choleh and
צער, tzaar, between sick and and pain, being in like, you know,
in discomfort and pain is different than being sick and so on.
That's one issue.
Then you have the מפרק כלאחר יד mesfarek ke-lachar yad and the
צער. tzaar. You have like, you know, two, right.
Well no of course you need to do the כלאחר יד ke-lachar
yad or else it's דאורייתא. De-oraisa דאורייתא doraita, would not be allowed
unless it's סכנה. sakana. כלאחר יד Ke-lachar yad makes it דרבנן. de-rabbanan.
Okay good, we got down to דרבנן. de-rabbanan. When can you do
איסורי דרבנן issurei de-rabbanan on שבת and יום טוב, Yom Tov, right?
Is צער tzaar enough or not? Exactly. So this גמרא Gemara seems
יום טוב, Yom Tov, צער tzaar is enough, שבת not. תוספות Tosafot
points out other גמרות Gemoras that seem to say that צער tzaar
is enough even for שבת. Now the other thing is, is this
an איסור דאורייתא issur de-oraisa like I was saying before? So if
you take a look at the תוספות, Tosafot, it sounds like it
is, sounds like you needed the כלאחר יד ke-lachar yad to make
it a דרבנן. de-rabbanan. But you take a look at the beginning
of תוספות קסבר דהוה מפרק כלאחר יד, Tosafot kasavar de-hava mesfarek ke-lachar
yad, so it says ואם תאמר ואפילו לא הוי כלאחר יד נמי,
ve-im tomar ve-afillu lo havei ke-lachar yad nami, even if it wasn't
an unusual way, דאין דיש אלא בגידולי קרקע, de-ein dish ella be-gidulei
karka, but this prohibition of threshing only applies by things that grow
from the ground and it shouldn't apply to animals. And he has
a whole long discussion, תוספות Tosafot says, you're right, you know what,
maybe this is only according to one opinion, but maybe actually it
would always be דרבנן de-rabbanan because it only applies to things that
grow from the ground. So when it comes to a woman expressing
milk, there's two reasons to argue why it would be a דרבנן
de-rabbanan to begin with. Number one is that she's not גידולי קרקע
gidulei karka and this is and against this גמרא, Gemara. against, that's
true, and
against this גמרא we rule that דש dish would only apply biblically
by things that grow from the ground. Number one. And number two,
by an animal, suckling directly is the שינוי, shinui, right? The normal
way for us as humans to get milk out of an animal
is by milking it with the hand. But for a woman it's
the opposite. Nursing a child, the suckling of the child is the
natural way and the expressing by the hands could be argued as
the כלאחר יד. ke-lachar yad. Okay. So therefore that's very important in
the question around women expressing milk on שבת. Okay, moving back to
the גמרא. תא
שמע. Ta shema. Back to figuring out whether we have to intervene
when minors are sinning and particularly we focus on the example of
eating טרפות treifos and we're going to, well, we already had examples
before יונק שקץ, yonek sheketz, so then we're probably going to see
why because of this case is very much a טרפות treifos case.
תא שמע לא תאכלום. Ta shema: lo sochlum. This is by the
eating of טרפות, treifos, of, of שרצים. shretzim. So כי שקץ הם,
ki sheketz heim, because they're an abomination. So the rabbinic דרשה drasha
is לא תאכילום, lo sachilum, do not feed them, להזהיר גדולים על
הקטנים, lehazhir gedolim al ha-ketanim, that adults have a responsibility vis-à-vis minors.
So when it says they have a responsibility, מאי לאו דאמר ליה
לא תאכל? mai lav de-amar lei lo sochal? Doesn't that mean they
have to say to them don't eat, it's טרף, treif, they have
to intervene? לא דלא ליספי ליה בידי. Lo, de-lo lispei lei be-yadei.
לא דלא לספו להו בידי, lo delo lispai leh bayadai, no, maybe
it just means don't feed, but maybe it doesn't mean don't eat,
you have to intervene? תא שמע, tashma, let's try again. כי נפש
מכם לא תאכל דם, ki nefesh mikem lo tokhal dam, any soul
from among you shall not eat blood. Again, the rabbinic דרשה derasha
is להזהיר גדולים על הקטנים, lehazhir gedolim al haktanim, that the adults
have responsibility to the minors. So it sounds like responsibility means you
have to intervene. מאי לאו דאמרו להו לא תאכלו, mai lav de-amru
lehu lo tokhlu, it must be that they're telling them don't eat.
לא דלא לספו להו בידי, lo delo lispai leh bayadai, no, it
means don't feed them, but not that they have to intervene. תא
שמע, tashma, אמור ואמרת, emor ve-amarta, this is by the כהנים. kohanim.
I read, אמור ואמרת, emor ve-amarta, you know,
אמור אל הכהנים בני אהרן ואמרת אליהם לנפש לא יטמא בעמיו, emor
el hakohanim benei Aharon ve-amarta aleihem lenefesh lo yitama be-amav, about becoming
טמא. tamei. So what's אמור ואמרת? emor ve-amarta? Say to someone else.
להזהיר גדולים על הקטנים, lehazhir gedolim al haktanim, to tell the adults
they have a responsibility. מאי לאו דאמרו להו לא תטמאו?
mai lav de-amru
lehu lo titmau?
Yeah, well that will be an answer the גמרא. מאי לאו דאמרו
להו לא תטמאו, mai lav de-amru lehu lo titmau, doesn't it mean
that they have to actually stop them from becoming טמא? tamei? לא
דלא ליטמו להו בידי, lo delo litmu lehu beyadayim, no, it means
don't do it actively. So although all three of these cases does
very much seem like you have an active responsibility, the גמרא is
going to say no, all it might mean is don't actively do
it, but not that there's a problem about being passive. וצריכי, ve-tzrichi,
and you need to tell me all three cases. דאשמינן שקצים, de-ashminan
shekatzim, had it just told me the case about the insects, or
whatever the rodents, משום דאיסורן במשהו, mishum de-issuran be-mashehu, because even a
small amount you can transgress. תוספות tosafot says what that means is
even if you eat just one ant, because it's a בריה, biryah,
it's a whole item. So a whole item, even if it's less
than a כזית, kezayit, you would transgress. Okay, אבל דם דעדי איכא
רביעית, aval dam de-adi ika reviit, but דם, dam, that you need
a more amount, you need a רביעית, reviit, like three and a
half ounces. So it's less severe, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe you
don't have a responsibility or it's not prohibited to feed them. דאשמינן
דם, de-ashminan dam, had it just said blood, משום דאיכא כרת, mishum
de-ika karet, because it's very weighty you get כרת. karet. אבל שרצים
אימא לא, aval sheratzim eima lo, but שרצים sheratzim is not punishable
by כרת, karet, it's a simple negative prohibition. ואשמינן הני תרתי, ve-ashminan
hani tartei, if it had just said don't feed or don't allow
in those two cases, משום דאיסורן שוה בכל, mishum de-issuran shaveh bakol,
because everybody is prohibited to eat these טרייף treif foods. אבל טומאה
אימא לא, aval tumah eima lo, but when it comes to impurity
of כהנים, kohanim, which is unique to כהנים, kohanim, maybe there isn't
a responsibility. It's not as big of an, it's not as global
of an issue. So that's why it needed to say that. ואשמינן
טומאה, ve-ashminan tumah, had it just said the case by כהנים, kohanim,
טומאת כהנים, tumat kohanim, כהנים שאני, kohanim shani, כהנים kohanim are different,
like Michael said, משום דריבה בהן מצות יתירות, mishum de-ribba bahen mitzvot
yeterot, they have so many extra מצוות that the idea that they
would have a special responsibility to protect their כהונה kehunah and to
prevent טומאה tumah would make sense by כהנים kohanim that have this
heightened responsibility.
אבל הני, aval hani, but the other cases of the טרייף treif
food, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe there wouldn't be a responsibility, צריכא.
tzricha. Okay, so we still don't know. All of those מדרש דרשות
midrash derashot sounded like you have a responsibility to intervene, or at
least reasonably it sounded like that. But the גמרא is saying no,
maybe it just means you're not allowed to actively do it. By
the way, there's an interesting question of what is the line between
intervening and doing it actively. Like if I go ahead and I
send my kid to a daycare that they feed טרייף treif food,
am I just not intervening or am I feeding him the טרייף
treif food? Okay, right? Interesting question. What is מידי, literally putting in
the mouth? Right, at what stage? Right, exactly. So, I mean the
case in the גמרא where I'm having them take a walk in
רשות הרבים is also a little bit creating the circumstances. But there
it sort of happens by itself as opposed to I'm sending them
to the school and they're being fed. Exactly. Exactly. Something like that.
Right, but again, these are minors, so that's the question. Okay, and
again, what should be noted is that the simple גמרא here assumes
that it would be the same, seems like it's talking even with
the parent involved and it would, does not seem to recognize a
special responsibility with the parents. Okay, so let's see what now we're
going to see what this has to do with our סוגיא. Let's
take a look. תא שמע, tashma, שני אחים, shenei achim, two brothers,
אחד פקח ואחד חרש, echad pikeach ve-echad cheresh, נשואין שתי אחיות פקחות,
nessuin shetei achayot pikechot, one is hearing and one is deaf, married
to two hearing sisters. מת חרש בעל פקחת, met cheresh baal pikechet,
the deaf brother dies. מה יעשה פקח בעל פקחת? mah yaaseh pikeach
baal pikechet? What does the hearing brother do? So he's married to
one woman דאורייתא, doraita and the other woman is his wife's sister.
So that's easy. תצא משום אחות אשה. teitzei mishum achot isha. The
woman leaves because she doesn't need יבום yibbum and חליצה, chalitzah, it's
his wife's sister.
מת פקח בעל פקחת. met pikeach baal pikechet. Let's say however the
hearing brother dies. So מה יעשה חרש בעל פקחת? mah yaaseh cheresh
baal pikechet? What does the deaf brother do? Now the deaf brother
is married rabbinically to this woman's sister and he has a דאורייתא
obligation of יבום. yibbum. So what can he do? מה יעשה, mah
yaaseh, wait, פקח, pikeach, מה יעשה חרש בעל פקחת. mah yaaseh cheresh
baal pikechet. מוציא
את אשתו בגט. motzi et ishto be-get. He has to give his
wife a גט because to stay married to him it would be
a case of אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. אשת אחיו אסורה עליו לעולם.
eshet achiv asurah alav leolam. And his brother's wife is forbidden to
him. Can't do חליצה chalitzah because he's a חרש. cheresh. Can't do
יבום yibbum because it's אחות אשה. achot isha. Okay, right, so everybody
remember that case? I'm not going to review it if you don't
remember it anyway. The גמרא's question is, אמאי מוציא את אשתו בגט?
amai motzi et ishto be-get? Why does he have to divorce his
wife? Well we said he has to divorce his wife because it's
אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. Who cares? He's a חרש. cheresh. Right? So
if we don't have to intervene when a קטן does sins, we
shouldn't have to intervene when a חרש cheresh does sins. So let
him Okay, so what if he's sinning? Okay, well so what if
it's אחות זקוקתו? achoz zekukaso? So the גמרא says אמאי מוציא
אשתו בגט?
Amai motzi
ishto beget?
תיתיב קמיה? Teisiv kabei? קטן הכא דאכיל נבלות הוא. Katan ocha de-achil
neveilos hu. So the גמרא says: No, משום איסורא דידה. mishum issura
didah. What? She is not a deaf person. She is an adult
woman and therefore she's also prohibited to have sex in a context
of אחות זקוקתו. achoz zekukaso. So therefore we won't allow it. Okay,
תא שמע, ta shma, let's try again and now we're going to
deal with a case where she's the חרשת and he's not. שני
אחים פקחים נשואים לשתי אחיות אחת פקחת ואחת חרשת. Shnei achim pikchim
nesuyim lishtei achayos achas pikachas ve-achas chereshes. Two hearing brothers married to
two sisters, one is hearing and one is not. מת פקח בעל
חרשת, Meis pikach ba'al chereshes, so the hearing, so
the husband of the deaf sister dies. מה יעשה פקח בעל פקחת?
Mah ya'aseh pikach ba'al pikachas? What does the guy married to the
hearing sister do? So he is biblically married to this woman's sister,
so she just walks away. So תצא משום אחות אשה. Tetzei mishum
achoz isha. מת פקח בעל פקחת. Meis pikach ba'al pikachas. Now if
the hearing brother dies, מה יעשה פקח בעל חרשת? Mah ya'aseh pikach
ba'al chereshes? What does the brother married to the deaf woman do?
So he has a biblical obligation of יבום yibum for his brother's
wife, but he is rabbinically married to the sister. So again he's
like stuck. So in this case, what does he do? מוציא אשתו
בגט. Motzi ishto beget. He has to give his wife a גט
because it would be אחות זקוקתו. achoz zekukaso. ואשת אחיו בחליצה, Ve-eshes
achiv bachalitzah, but at least here he can do חליצה chalitzah because
since she is hearing, he is able to do חליצה chalitzah with
his brother's wife. So now the גמרא same question: Why did he
have to divorce his wife? ואמאי מוציא אשתו בגט? Ve-amai motzi ishto
beget? תיתיב קמיה? Teisiv kabei? Let her sit by him. קטן אוכל
נבלות הוא. Katan ochel neveilos hu.
His wife is a חרשת, which means she's not obligated, so we
shouldn't care about her doing עבירות. aveiros. Let her stay by him.
Of course the answer is: We don't care about her doing עבירות,
aveiros, we care about him doing עבירות. aveiros. Right? So the גמרא
says: No, משום איסורא דידיה. mishum issura deilei. No, because of him.
Okay,
so in either case we won't tolerate the marriage because one of
them is a non-חרש. cheresh. Of course now the גמרא—this is all
just a set up for the last question, which is when they're
both חרשים cherashim and we're still not going to allow it. Okay?
So the גמרא says: תא שמע. ta shma. אמר רבא תא שמע.
Amar Rava ta shma. Come and hear. שני אחים אחד חרש ואחד
פקח, Shnei achim echad cheresh ve-echad pikach, two brothers, one hearing and
one deaf. נשואים לשתי אחיות אחת פקחת ואחת חרשת, Nesuyim lishtei achayos
achas pikachas ve-achas chereshes, one hearing and one deaf and they match.
מת חרש בעל
חרשת, Meis cheresh ba'al chereshes, if the deaf brother dies, מה יעשה
פקח בעל פקחת? Mah ya'aseh pikach ba'al pikachas? The wife is his
wife's sister and he's biblically—his biblical wife's sister, so she just walks
away. תצא משום אחות אשה. Tetzei mishum achoz isha. מת פקח בעל
פקחת. Meis pikach ba'al pikachas. If the hearing brother married to the
hearing woman dies, מה יעשה חרש בעל חרשת? Mah ya'aseh cheresh ba'al
chereshes?
What does the חרש cheresh do? Okay, so it's a case of
again his rabbinic wife's sister, she can't walk away because it's only
rabbinic, it's אחות אשה achoz isha and אחות זקוקתו. achoz zekukaso. What
is he going to do? מה יעשה? Mah ya'aseh? So מוציא אשתו
בגט. Motzi ishto beget. Again
he has to give his wife a גט. He can give his
wife a גט because he only married her rabbinically, he can divorce
her rabbinically. ואשת אחיו אסורה עליו לעולם, Ve-eshes achiv asura alav le-olam,
and his brother's wife is always forbidden, he can't do חליצה chalitzah
because he's a חרש, cheresh, and he can't do יבום yibum because
it's אחות אשה. achoz isha. She's always forbidden. והכא. Ve-hacha. So what's
the problem? Both of them are deaf. והכא דלאו איסורא דידה איכא
ולאו איסורא דידיה איכא. Ve-hacha dela issura didah ika velo issura deilei
ika. It's not her prohibition, not her prohibition, not his prohibition. Right?
So why do we not allow this? And, right, so this, and
so why should we not allow this? It sounds like בית דין
has to intervene because we're not allowing this. וקתני מוציא אשתו בגט,
Ve-kasni motzi ishto beget, we demand a גט. אמר רב שמעיה גזירה
משום אחות יבמה לשוק. Amar Rav Shemaya gezeira mishum achoz yevama lashuk.
Actually
the reason we demand a גט has nothing to do with the
fact that we can't allow them to live together. We, let them
live together, we don't care that they're doing—that it's an עבירה, aveirah
it's not our responsibility, they're not בר דעת. The problem is if
they live together סתם, stam, people will assume: Why was there no
חליצה, chalitzah, why was there no גט, whatever? They'll assume: Oh, because
the wife's sister, right, these two are continuing to live together, right,
and there was no גט, that must mean that it's considered a
real marriage and therefore the other woman wasn't an issue because it
was his wife's sister and she's an ערוה ervah and she walks
away. And from—and therefore they'll allow the יבמה yevama to marry somebody
else and she's not allowed to marry somebody else because this marriage
here is only דרבנן derabbanan and it's not a real biblical case
of wife's sister. So if we don't problematize the current marriage, acknowledging
that it's only rabbinic and there's a wife's sister's problem here, right,
if we don't problematize that people will think that the sister-in-law is
free to go ahead and marry somebody else. It's a completely normal
case of wife's sister. So we have to say: No, this isn't
normal, it's actually a problem, and because it's a problem and there's
an עבירה aveirah, here they have to get divorced and they'll understand
the story of the sister-in-law. But really, yes it is an עבירה,
aveirah but really we might not have to intervene. So the גמרא
does not conclude whether בית דין has to intervene in a case
of a biblical עבירה aveira. that a minor is doing, and there's
obviously a lot of very important הלכתי halachic implications about this and
also about whether it would be different when a parent would be
involved. הדרן עלך החרש. Hadran alach hacheresh. Yes, we actually got through
that. I wanted to... Yes?
I mean, I understand this last case where they could have
said קטן אוכל נבילות katan ochal neveilos but it's a גזירה. gezeira.
But in the previous two cases they're גדולים gedolim like the husband
and the wife. Yeah, how can they compare?
That's what the גמרא's answer was. That maybe one of them was
a חרש, cheresh, but the other was not. So it's not relevant
because one of them is still... that's what I meant. Yeah. One
of them is still doing an עבירה. Okay, let's start the next
פרק. perek Okay, two פרקים prokim to go. This whole פרק perek
was a very short one if you didn't notice that. Okay, there
are three פרקים prokim that are called האישה, Ha-isha, if you might
remember, right? We had way back one האישה רבה, Ha-isha Rabba, the
big האישה, Ha-isha, okay, she wasn't big, the פרק was big, okay.
That was all about reports about her husband having died and you
know and so on and תצא מזו ומזו teitzei mizu umizu and
all that. And now we're going to get with again the last
two פרקים prokim also about women, a woman reporting that her husband
died or reports of a death of her husband. One is האישה
שלום, Ha-isha Shalom, we'll see why it's called that in a minute,
and the last one is האישה בתרא Ha-isha Batra which means last
one. So there are three האישה Ha-isha פרקים. prokim. Let's take a
look at ours. האישה שהלכה היא ובעלה למדינת הים: Ha-isha she-halcha hi
u-va-ala le-medinas hayam: a woman she and her husband went to a
overseas. שלום בינו לבינה: Shalom beino leveina: they were, their marriage was
good as far as we knew. ושלום בעולם: v-shalom ba-olam: and there
was peace in the world. ובאה ואמרה מת בעלי: U-va-a v-amra meis
ba-ali: and she came back and she said, my husband died. תינשא:
Tinasei: she can get married, we believe her. מת בעלי: Meis ba-ali:
or she says her husband died, תתייבם: tisyabeim: she can do ייבום.
yibbum. Now if one of those factors is not present: שלום בינו
לבינה ומלחמה בעולם: Shalom beino leveina u-milchama ba-olam:
their marriage is good but there's a war in the world, or
קטטה בינו לבינה ושלום בעולם: ktata beino leveina v-shalom ba-olam:
they are clearly having a stressful, fighting marriage, even if it's peace
in the world, ובאה ואמרה מת בעלי u-va-a v-amra meis ba-ali and
she says her husband died, אינה נאמנת: eina ne-emenes: she's not believed.
Now why not? In the case when there's a war in the
world, because we're afraid that there's a war and her husband didn't
return, let's say, from war, or you know, they were under siege
or whatever, that she will think her husband is dead when she's
not. That's what the גמרא is going to say is אומרה בדדמי.
omra bididamei. So if it's those type of of circumstances, right, we
we cannot assume like under normal cases the guy says, my husband
died, my husband died, he died on his hospital bed, we buried
him or whatever. But in case of war, my husband died, she
might be just the way she's interpreting what happened. Number one. Number
two is if there's peace in the world but they're fighting, she
might just סתם stam be lying. Now why would she be lying?
She'll have to deal with all the consequences. Well רש"י Rashi says
if she goes ahead and gets remarried and her husband shows up,
then her husband's going to be forced to divorce her because she's
now been living with another man. So maybe she's intentionally lying. All
right, whatever, but maybe she's not concerned about that. Okay, now, so
אינה נאמנת. eina ne-emenes. רבי יהודה אומר לעולם אינה נאמנת: Rabbi Yehuda
omer l-olam eina ne-emenes: even when there's peace in the world she's
not believed and they're having a good marriage, אלא אם כן באה
בוכה ובגדיה קרועים: ela im kein ba-a bocha u-vgadeha kru-im:
only if there's like supporting evidence, she comes back crying and her
garments are rent.
And she's like looking upbeat from back to normal?
Yeah, exactly. Only if there's some supporting evidence. אמרו לו, Amru lo,
they said back to him, אחת זו ואחת זו תינשא: achas zu
v-achas zu tinasei: either way she can get married. Let's just read
one line of the גמרא. תנא שלום בינו לבינה משום ד... Tanna
shalom beino leveina mishum d-... Why did it have to say they
have peace in the world, or they have peace. You know, that's
the normal situation. No, משום דקבעי למיתני קטטה בינו לבינה: mishum d-kaba-ei
lemitni ktata beino leveina: because it wanted to contrast it to when
they're fighting. תנא שלום בעולם: Tanna shalom ba-olam: it said peace in
the
world, משום דקבעי למיתני מלחמה בעולם: mishum d-kaba-ei lemitni milchama ba-olam:
it wanted to contrast it. ואמר רבא מאי טעמא דמלחמה: V-amar Rava
mai ta-ama d-milchama: why
if their marriage is good is it a problem if there's a
war in the world and she says my husband died? משום דאמרה
בדדמי: Mishum d-amra bididamei:
she says based on דמי, damei, דמי damei means similar, she says
based on like an impression that she had, imprecision, it's not with
absolute with precise knowledge. סלקא דעתה, Salka daitah,
she figures, look, בכל הני דאיקטול הוא פלט: bechol hanei d-iktal hu
palat: all those people died, my husband would be the one guy
that escaped? Right, a whole battalion went and was wiped out and
my husband was among them. Of course he's dead. That's what she
assumes. אם תימצי לומר כיון דשלום בינו לבינה נטרה עד דחזיא: Im
timtzi lomar keivan d-shalom beino leveina natra ad de-chazya:
if you were to say that and and that
look, if there's peace between the two of them, you know, she
would wait until she actually saw the husband actually dead before she
reported it. That's not always possible. זימנין דמחוו ליה בגירא: Zimnin d-machvu
lei bigira: sometimes he'll be shot by an arrow, או ברומחא: o
vi-rumcha: or spear, וסברה וודאי מת: v-savra vadai meis: and
she'll assume he died. Like you know, she's there, she's under siege,
arrows are flying, she can't wait around to see if he's dead,
right, she just sees that you know, he's been mortally wounded.
ואיכא דעבדי סמטרי וחיי: V-ika d-avdi samtrei v-chayei: and
some people can make you know, bandages and types of medicine and
maybe he actually will will live. So therefore, we even though she
would not intentionally lie, it's very reasonable in case of war that
you'll assume he definitely died when he didn't. And we will continue
seeing more of this tomorrow. Ah, we actually caught up more or
less.